A Guide to the National Committee on United States-China Relations records, RG 9, Accession 9 FA1191
Rockefeller Archive Center
National Committee on United States-China Relations records, RG 9, Accession 9
1948-2012
Rockefeller Archive Center
National Committee on United States-China Relations
FA1191
25.75 Cubic Feet 67 containers
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist. When requesting audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact an RAC archivist for further instruction.
Arrangement
The records of the National Committee on United States – China Relations are divided into ten record groups, which reflect the order in which the records were received (but which are otherwise an artificial distinction). The records are sorted intellectually into series, which carry over through all record groups, but they have received minimal physical rearrangement. RG 9 of the NCUSCR records is arranged into thirteen series: 1 - Events; 2 - Exchanges - General; 3 - Exchanges to China; 4 - Exchanges from China; 5 - Conferences, Seminars, Workshops, and Dialogues; 6 - Publications and Reports; 8 - Programs, Projects, and Proposals; 9 - Ping Pong Diplomacy; 10 - Development; 11 – Board of Directors, Committees, and Members records; 14 – NCUSCR Presidents' Files; 15 – Clippings and Reference; and 16 - Special Formats - General.
Scope and Contents
RG 9, the final segment of document files in the NCUSCR records, includes materials from multiple series and notably contains several early organizational and program files that the National Committee considered historical records. In addition to materials in the Board of Directors, Committees, and Members files, RG 9 includes records of the seminal April 1965 Conference on the United States and China. The Presidents' Files series contains Arthur H. Rosen's chronological files for the full period of his tenure, 1975-1987. Other materials of note include reference and reports files on various Travelers to China and records of NCUSCR Members' Trips to China; records of the University Field Staffs, mainly for the 1970s; the Civil Society in China project, circa 1997-2000; and public relations, press, and correspondence files for the Chinese Table Tennis Delegation visit to the U.S. in 1972. Finally, the Clippings and Reference series includes, among other materials, a compilation of U.S. Government Statements on China, from 1948 to the late 1960s, as well as extensive files documenting the events surrounding the Tiananmen Square uprising and reaction to them.
- Events, 1985-2011; 1; 0.76 Cubic Feet 2 letter document boxes
  - Proposed Fundraising Dinner, 1985 September 26 (Box 52, Folder 506)
    Scope and Contents
    Proposed dinner honoring George Schultz; invitation to Barbara Bush (regrets); Foreign Minister Wu possible speaker.
  - Proposed Nixon Fundraiser, 1989 -1990 (Box 52, Folder 507)
    NCUSCR invitations to Richard Nixon to speak at a dinner or meeting. Correspondence dated November 1989.
  - Ambassadors Zhu Qizhen and Li Daoyu Meeting with David Rockefeller, 2001 February 9 (Box 52, Folder 508)
  - Other Organizations - Universities Service Centre (Hong Kong), 2004 (Box 52, Folder 509)
    Talks presented at program commemorating the fortieth anniversary of the Universities Service Center.
  - Scholar Orientation Program Reunions, 1996 June 23; June 29 1996 (Box 61, Folder 592)
    Sample programs for reunions Beijing and Shanghai.
  - Metropolitan Opera - Nixon in China, 2011 January 31 (Box 61, Folder 593)
    Dress rehearsal and banquet in celebration of Nixon in China. It is not clear whether there was any NCUSCR involvement with regard to this event.
- Exchanges - General, 1971-2012; 2; 5.76 Cubic Feet
  Series 2, Exchanges - General, in RG 9, contains collected reports and reference files on exchanges and visits to - and in some cases from - China by individuals and other (non-NCUCSCR) sponsoring organizations, from the early 1970s to the early 1980s, especially. Materials include lists of travelers to China and files of trip reports, sorted by subject. Also significant are policy memos and formal exchange proposals the National Committee negotiated with the Chinese government for the period from the early 1970s up to 1983. Series 2 also includes various briefing materials; an alphabetical card file of individual and institutional contacts in the U.S. with connections to China, for the 1970s; and a clippings card file on Chinese delegations to other countries, 1971-1977.
  - Other Organizations - Broadcasting Delegation from China, 1973-1974 (Box 11, Folder 118)
    Invitation from three main U. S. networks proposing that a delegation of broadcast journalists visit from China.
  - Other Organizations - Seiji Ozawa, 1976-1977 (Box 11, Folder 119)
    Reference to Ozawa's visit to China in December 1976, and invitation for Chinese musicians to come to Tanglewood in 1977.
  - Other Organizations - Philadelphia World Affairs Council Delegation, 1977-1978 (Box 11, Folder 120)
    Trip to China, fall 1977; proposed meeting with Chinese visitors, spring 1978.
  - Other Organizations - Geographers Delegation (Ohio Academy of Sciences), 1977-1978 (Box 11, Folder 121)
    Geographers delegation, August 1977. A delegation of Chinese geographers paid a return visit to the U.S., September - November 1978.
  - Other Organizations - Luce Scholars Program, 1978 (Box 11, Folder 122)
    Luce Foundation request proposing a Luce Scholars visit to China in July 1979.
  - Educational and Cultural Exchanges - Background Papers and Memos, 1972-1974 (Box 11, Folder 123)
  - National Committee Policy on Exchanges, 1972; 1977 (Box 11, Folder 124)
    The file includes correspondence, notes on meetings, and draft position papers on issues pertaining to educational and cultural exchanges with the PRC.
  - National Committee Relations with the U. S. Government concerning Exchanges, 1973-1975 (Box 11, Folder 125)
    See also folders 123 - 124, for other materials pertaining to government relations with respect to exchange programs.
  - National Committee Status after Normalization, 1978-1979 (Box 11, Folder 126)
    Correspondence file. The U. S. and the PRC announced their intention to establish diplomatic relations on December 15, 1978, and signed a joint communique to that effect on January 1, 1979.
  - Background Correspondence, Memos, and Proposals on Exchanges, 1972-1975 (Box 12, Folder 127)
    Includes lists of exchanges and exchange proposals for 1973-1975.
  - Exchange Proposals for 1974 - Memos, 1973 (Box 12, Folder 128)
    Proposals for U. S. exchange delegations to China from Community Organizations, Agricultural and Rural Youth Leaders, the Performing Arts, University and College Presidents and Officers, Foundation Executives, and World Affairs Organizations. File includes memos on representative organizations within each these broader groups.
  - Performing Arts Exchange Proposals (General), 1973; Still Images: Eleven black-and-white 5x7 - 8x10 glossy prints. (Box 12, Folder 129)
    Publicity and other material on dance and other performing arts groups. Includes materials on the Columbus Boychoir, Paul Taylor Dance Company, the Children's Theatre Company of the Minneapolis Institute of Arts, Jos? Lim›n Dance Company, and University of Michigan Chamber Choir. File includes black and white publicity photos of the Children's Theatre, the Paul Taylor and Jos? Lim›n dance companies, and the Michigan Chamber Choir.
  - Performing Arts Exchange Proposals (General), 1973-1974; 1980 (Box 12, Folder 130)
    Includes memos on dance companies; 1974 Coordinated Residency Touring Program Directory of Dance Companies; and 1980 inquiries concerning music exchanges.
  - Exchange Proposals to the Chinese for 1976, 1975-1976 (Box 12, Folder 131)
    The National Committee presented its exchange proposals to the Liaison Office in a letter of October 2, 1975.
  - Exchange Proposals, Principles, and Objectives for 1976, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 133)
    File consists of multiple drafts of proposals, statements of principles of the exchange program, and assessments of the exchange experience.
  - Exchange Proposals to the Chinese for 1977, 1976-1977 (Box 13, Folder 134)
  - Exchange Proposals for 1978, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 135)
  - Exchange Proposals for 1979, 1978-1979 (Box 13, Folder 136)
  - Exchange Agreements and Proposals (Califano and Mondale Education Proposals), 1979-1981 (Box 13, Folder 137)
    Memoranda of understanding with the PRC concerning Education Exchanges for 1980-1981, signed by Joseph Califano, U. S. secretary of Health, Education, and Welfare, June 23, 1979; and by Walter Mondale, August 23, 1979. File includes correspondence concerning agreements, exchange proposals, and planning.
  - Exchange Proposals for 1980, 1979-1980 (Box 13, Folder 138)
  - Exchange Proposals for 1981, 1980-1981 (Box 13, Folder 139)
  - Exchange Proposals for 1982, 1981-1982 (Box 13, Folder 140)
  - Exchange Proposals for 1983 (Box 13, Folder 141)
  - United States - PRC Implementing Accord for Cultural Exchange in 1982 and 1983 (News Release), 1981 September 5 (Box 13, Folder 142)
    Accord to carry out the activities provided for under the U. S. - PRC Cultural Agreement of January 31, 1979.
  - U. S. International Communications Agency Cables, 1979 - 1983 May (Box 13, Folder 143-144)
    Communications between USICA /USIA and the U. S. embassy in Beijing concerning exchanges. The USICA was created in 1978 with the merger of the U. S. Information Agency and the Bureau of Educational and Cultural Affairs of the Department of State. Starting in August 1982, it was again known as the U. S. Information Agency.
  - Recent U. S. Travelers to China (Summary Lists), 1972-1980 (Box 14, Folder 145)
    Includes list of Foreign Delegations to the PRC, 1979-1980; Congressional Delegations, 1972-1979; and Facilitated Exchanges, 1972-1978.
  - Recent U. S. Travelers to China (Clippings, by Type of Visit), circa 1972 - 1980 (Box 14, Folder 146-147)
    File sorted by subject area: Arts, Business, Education, Government, Sports, etc.
  - Recent U. S. Travelers to China (Clippings, by Type of Visit), 1981-1982 (Box 14, Folder 148)
  - Mansfield-Scott Trip to China: Anne Fitzgerald Diary, 1972 May (Box 14, Folder 149)
    Anne Fitzgerald accompanied Senators Mike Mansfield and Hugh Scott on their visit to China, April 18 - May 3, 1972.
  - Thomas Stapleton, Notes by a Visitor to China (Second - Third Series), 1964; 1973 (Box 14, Folder 150-151)
    Stapleton was a professor of pediatrics at the University of Sydney.
  - Report of the CSCPRC Economics Delegation to the People's Republic of China (1979 October 8-27), 1980 (Box 14, Folder 152)
    CSCPRC - Committee for Scholarly Communication with the People's Republic of China.
  - Committee for Scholarly Communication with the People's Republic of China (CSCPRC) Beijing Office Archive, 1983-1985 (Box 15, Folder 153-154)
    The CSCPRC, jointly with the National Academy of Sciences, opened an office in Beijing on July 19, 1985. The file consists of the documentary record, or "archive," of the office's creation and opening.
  - David J. Finkelstein, Reports and Papers on China and Asia, 1975 -1976 (Box 26, Folder 246)
    "Reflections on China" (report on his private visit to China in the summer of 1975). File also includes reports on Taiwan, Korea, and Burma. Finkelstein was a Ford Foundation program officer for Asia.
  - Trip Reports - Arts, 1976-1980; Still Image: 8x10 black and white print (Box 26, Folder 253)
    Including University of Minnesota Concert Band, 1980 (includes group photo); Brown University Chorus, 1979; Museum of the American China Trade, 1978; Louis Dupree, Archeological Tour, April 1978; Chou Wen-chung visit, 1977 November; John Woolfenden, "A Return to China via Bridge of Art" (Nancy Stilwell Easterbrook and Alison Stilwell Cameron visit, 1976).
  - Trip Reports - Arts - Philadelphia Orchestra, 1973 (Box 26, Folder 254)
    American press coverage - articles by Harold Schonberg and Daniel Webster. For Sue E. Barber, "Music and Politics: The Philadelphia Orchestra in the People's Republic of China," M. A. thesis, August 1977, see NCUSCR, RG 4, FA1186, box 17, folder 129.
  - Trip Reports - Business and Economics, 1975-1981 (Box 26, Folder 255)
    Metallurgy delegation, November 1981; Parsons Brinckerhoff trip to China, October 1978; Way W. Lee report on Canton Trade Fair, Fall 1975; John B. Fairchild, Invitation to China, 1975 (Canton Trade Fair, Bill Blass).
  - Trip Reports - Business and Economics (Jacobson), 1972 November 9 - December 21 (Box 26, Folder 256)
    Report on Visit to the PRC, by David J. Jacobson, Chair, Chinese People's Industries Corporation, January 22, 1973.
  - Trip Reports - Education, 1974-1981 (Box 27, Folder 257)
    Also includes 1981 Observations on American Education, by Wang Yingjie.
  - Trip Reports - Education - Study Group on Relations between Education and Work in the PRC, 1978 April 25 - May 15 (Box 27, Folder 258)
    Study group chaired by Clark Kerr. File includes the extended version of the Study Group Report.
  - Trip Reports - Education - University of Minnesota, Second Delegation to the PRC, 1980 August 29 - September 18 (Box 27, Folder 259)
    "Strengthening Educational Links with China." Bound volume report on the delegation and on 1980 China Program activities.
  - Trip Reports - Government and Politics, 1972-1978 (Box 27, Folder 260-261)
    Includes Senators Mike Mansfield and Hugh Scott, April - May 1972; Hale Boggs and Gerald R. Ford, June - July 1972; Senator and Mrs. Warren Magnuson, China Diary, July 1973; Senator Henry Jackson report, July 1974; Seventh Congressional Delegation, August 1975; Delegation of Congresswomen, December 1975 - January 1976; Study Mission report, April 1976; Senator Hugh Scott report, July 1976; Fact-Finding Mission to the Far East, November 1976; China and the Chinese: Compendium of Papers, November 1976; Senator Edward M. Kennedy report, January 1978; International Relations delegation, July 1978; Joseph G. Whelan, Report on China Trip, 1981.
  - Trip Reports - Government and Politics, 1976-1981 (Box 27, Folder 262)
    State legislatures delegations, 1976-1977; American Bar Association, 1978; Jonathan Kaufman, China Council Project on China's Foreign Relations trip, August 1981. Also Includes pamphlet on Agricultural Mechanization in China: The Administrative Impact, by Steven Butler, 1978.
  - Trip Reports - Journalistic, 1967; 1971-1981 (Box 27, Folder 263)
    Includes reports, among others, by R. V. Denenberg, "Peace on Dong Jiadu Street" (1981); John Woolfenden (1979); Herb Caen (1978); Drew Middleton (1976); Robert L. Bartley (1976); Ann Landers (1974, American Medical Association delegation); Hobert Duncan (April 1973); Barbara Tuchman (July 1972); John S. Service (September - November 1971); Ross Terrill (June-Juloy 1971); William Attwood (1971); and Tadao Ishikawa (1967).
  - Trip Reports - Joseph Alsop, "Matter of Fact" Columns from China, 1972 November - 1973 January (Box 28, Folder 264)
  - Trip Reports - American Society of Newspaper Editors (ASNE), First Delegation, 1972 September - October (Box 28, Folder 265)
  - Trip Reports - American Society of Newspaper Editors (ASNE), Second Delegation, 1975 May - June (Box 28, Folder 266)
  - Trip Reports - American Society of Newspaper Editors (ASNE), Third Delegation, 1978 September - October (Box 28, Folder 267)
  - Trip Reports - Science, Medicine, and Technology, 1972-1978 (Box 28, Folder 268-269)
    Nicholas Lardy, China Trip Notes, 1978 (Hong Kong Family Planning Association delegation); John and Louise Rasmussen and Richard and Marian Diamond visit, 1977 (physics and medicine); Frederick S. Jaffe, China Trip Notes, 1977 (U. S. Birth Planning Study Group); Boel Berner, University of Lund, China's Science through Visitors' Eyes, 1975 June; Insect Control Delegation(CSC), 1975 August; Jesse Chia-Hsi Hwa visit, 1974; Water Resources Delegation report, 1974 August-September; W. Ross Cockrill trip report, 1974 April-May (Animal Production and Health Division, FAO); H. Ti Tien, Biophysical Society visit, 1972 November.
  - Trip Reports - Science, Medicine, and Technology, 1973-1980 (Box 28, Folder 270)
    Mainly reports relating to medicine and health. Includes report of the "Second Birth Planning Group" visit, November 2-20, 1978.
  - Rockefeller University Delegation Report, 1977 May 5-22 (Box 28, Folder 271)
  - Trip Reports - Sports, 1973-1980; 1985 (Box 29, Folder 272)
    Includes report on the Washington Bullets trip, August 20 - September 1, 1979; and U. S. Figure Skating Delegation, November 1980. Report on unidentified sports exchange, September 1985.
  - Marco Polo Television Film Project, 1981 (Box 36, Folder 340)
  - Other Delegations (General), 1975-1979; 1982; 1999 (Box 36, Folder 341)
    Chinese People's Association for Friendship with Foreign Countries (Youxie), September 1979; Bureau of Education, First Ministry of Machine Building delegation, April 1979; Chinese Geography delegation, September 24 - November 1, 1978; Chinese Technicians, 1978; Chinese Meteorological Society; Scientific and Technical Association delegation, 1975 October. Itinerary for Burlington Northern Far East Trip, (1982) June-July; State Legislators Study Tour to China, 1999 October.
  - Other Proposals - Television, Journalism, Educational Film, Music, 1982-1983 (Box 36, Folder 342)
    Report on Sino-Australian press seminar, Beijing, November 1981; proposal for Chinese television delegation; proposal for American Educational Film Festival in China, 1983; proposal for Chinese/American Musical, 1983.
  - Other Visits - Chinese Architectural Delegation, 1975 September 21 - October 12 (Box 36, Folder 343)
    Visit hosted by the American Institute of Architects.
  - Other Visits - Chinese Journalists Delegation, 1978 August - September (Box 36, Folder 344)
    Delegation sponsored by the American Society of Newspaper Editors (ASNE); Hsinhua journalists hosted by UPI and the AP.
  - Other Visits - Chinese Baseball (Invitation), 1979 March (Box 36, Folder 345)
    Invitation for Chinese baseball players and coaches to join major league teams in spring training. The Chinese were unable to accept the invitation for 1979.
  - Other Visits - Alvin Toffler Visit to China, 1983 January 2-17 (Box 36, Folder 346)
    Alvin and Heidi Toffler visit hosted by the Chinese Society for Future Studies.
  - Other Visits - Liu Zhongren Book Tour, 1985 March - July (Box 36, Folder 347)
    Book tour for his Two Years in the Melting Pot.The National Committee sponsored a discussion in New York on March 28, 1985.
  - China Briefing Kits - Early Versions, 1973-1976 (Box 52, Folder 510-511)
    Includes "Background Information for Travel to China," compiled by Eugene A. Theroux at the request of Joseph Alioto. Intended for use by a Mayors Delegation to China, planned for September 1975.
  - Briefing Packet on the People's Republic of China, 1978 January (Box 52, Folder 512)
    Prepared by the NCUSCR "for the Honorable Jan Carol Berris," 1978 January 26. Removed from ring binder.
  - Briefing Packet on the People's Republic of China prepared for the Boston Symphony Orchestra, 1979 February (Box 52, Folder 513)
  - U.S. - People's Republic of China Protocol File, 1979-1981 (Box 52, Folder 514)
    Agreements concerning cultural and educational exchanges, scientific and technical cooperation, environmental protection, and water resource management.
  - Early Education Exchanges and Programs, 1979-1988; 1992 (Box 52, Folder 515)
  - Memo on Education Delegations from China, 1986 (Box 52, Folder 516)
    Overview of four 1986 delegations, by unknown NCUSCR staff member.
  - Guides to Programs and Resources for Business and Educational Exchanges in China, circa 1994-1995 (Box 52, Folder 517)
    NCUSCR-produced guides to Teaching Programs and Study Programs in the PRC; Resource Lists for Doing Business in China and of Organizations Deling with China.
  - Office Visits, 1999-2012 (Box 52, Folder 518)
    Meetings at NCUSCR office with various delegations and visiting officials. Includes some notes on meetings.
  - Environmental NGOs - Programs and Reference, 1998-2000 (Box 53, Folder 519)
    Includes materials on the First NGO Forum on US - China Environmental Cooperation, 1999 September 2-3, Bethesda, MD
  - Journalists - Jan Berris Background File, 1984-1986 (Box 53, Folder 520)
  - Tibet - General Correspondence, Readings, and Clippings, 1995-2000 (Box 53, Folder 521)
  - Young Leaders Forum Banner for Astronaut Mark Kelly, 2006; Realia: Textile (Banner) (Box 53, Folder 522)
    Back-Up YLF Banner for Astronaut Mark Kelly (2003 YLF Fellow) to carry aboard Space Shuttle Discovery Mission to International Space Station in July 2006. Kelly was the Shuttle's pilot.
  - Program Reports, 1987 (Box 61, Folder 601)
    Reports on 1987 programs: Economic Journalists and Educational Exchange Officials delegations from China, and Education Programs in China; Report on Program of the Chinese Delegation to the 1987 U. S. - China Dialogue.
  - Correspondence (General), 1994; 2003 (Box 61, Folder 602)
    Two items: Letter from Angele M. Iovino, National Endowment for the Humanities, on her exchange experience, 1994; Jason Kindopp, NCUSCR resident scholar, to Ambassador Yang Jiechi, (2003), on arrest of Xiao Biguang and Zhang Yinan. Original folder labeled "Interesting Miscellaneous Correspondence."
  - Sidney Greenblatt Correspondence File, 1986-1987 (Box 61, Folder 603)
    Greenblatt served as an interpreter for various delegations from China. File consists mainly of follow-up correspondence to Greenblatt from delegates or delegation visits.
  - Outside Exchanges - Chinese Language Teaching Delegation, 1983-1986 (Box 61, Folder 604)
    Narrative report on University of Chicago Project, by Chih-ch'ao Chao. Delegation funded by the U. S. Department of Education.
  - Briefing Materials on China - General Background, 2005 June (Box 61, Folder 605)
    Section 2, "Background Materials," from an unidentified Briefing Book, revised June 1, 2005, 68 pp.
  - Student Interview Notes, circa 2004-2005 (Box 61, Folder 606)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted - confidential material. Open in 2028.
    Notes on interviews with American student applicants for unidentified program - possibly for the Student Leaders Exchange program.
  - Slides of China and Delegation Visits, 1974-1978; Still Images: 67 color slides, mounted on mylar slide pages. (Box 61, Folder 607)
    Color slides from three or more sets. Jan Berris and University and College Presidents Delegation, 1974 November, and with Tennis delegation in Canton, 1977; Chinese People's Institute of Foreign Affairs delegation to the U. S., 1977 June - July; Jan Berris photos of China; general images of China and the Chinese, circa 1977 November - 1978 April, some labeled "JP." Some images include captions.
  - Contacts File, 1973-1977 (Box 61, Folder 608)
    Lists and clippings, removed from Contacts Card File.
  - Contacts Card File, 1970s (Box 62)
    Alphabetical file on individuals, academics, and organizations in the U. S. with connections to China, and including delegations that have traveled to China.